Finding Aid for den Bleyker Family papers, 1828-1936
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
den Bleyker Family papers 1828-1936
Den Bleyker family.
(in 10 boxes)
9 linear feet
851056 Aa 2; UAx
Paulus den Bleyker family of Kalamazoo, Michigan. Papers of Paulus den Bleyker, his son John, John's wife, Anna Balch den Bleyker, and other family members relating to family and business affairs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Gertrude den Bleyker (donor no. 378 ) in 1938.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The den Bleyker family were earlier settlers to the so-called Dutch "kolonie" in Kalamazoo, Michigan. Paulus den Bleyker had come to the small community of Kalamazoo with his family and fellow immigrants in 1850, settled there, and commenced a life of farming, real estate dealings in Ottawa and Kalamazoo counties, and other business activities. His son John was a farmer, cattle breeder and director of the Kalamazoo National Bank.
The collection includes the correspondence and business papers of Paulus den Bleyker, papers of his son John den Bleyker and John's wife Anna Balch, Paulus' daughter, Martha, and other family members and descendents. Much of the correspondence is in Dutch, but an English calendar of these letters (in box 1) has been prepared by Harry DeVries and Effa Zwier.
Many of the papers for the years 1828-1851 are on affairs in Holland and the den Bleyker settlement near Kalamazoo. For the years 1851-1856, the correspondence deals with personal affairs, the building of a flour mill and a saw mill and land transactions. For the years 1856-1857, there are many letters from family and friends but the bulk of them concern den Bleyker's real estate dealings. For 1872 to 1936, the correspondence is of John and Anna Balch den Bleyker and relates to family and business.
Of special significance in the collection is the file of letters exchanged between Paulus den Bleyker and A.C. Van Raalte, the founder of the Dutch community in Holland, Michigan.
Subjects:
Den Bleyker family.; Dutch Americans--Michigan.; Michigan--Emigration and immigration.; Kalamazoo (Mich.); Voyages and travels.; Travelers.; Van Raalte, Albertus C. (Albertus Christiaan), 1811-1876.; Netherlands--Emigration and immigration.; Immigrants--Michigan.; Europe--Description and travel.; Michigan--Women--Kalamazoo.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Den Bleyker, Martha, d. 1930.; Den Bleyker family.; Stone, Lucinda Hinsdale, 1814-1900.
Contributors:
Den Bleyker, Anna Balch, b. 1840.; Den Bleyker, John, b. 1839.; Den Bleyker, Martha, d. 1930.; Den Bleyker, Paulus, 1804-1872.
Genre Terms:
Ambrotypes.; Photographs.
- Paulus den Bleyker
  - Calendar of the collection, largely the letters of Paulus den Bleyker 1828-1871, 7 volumes (Box 1)
    (The first three volumes and part of volume 4 exist in both typescript and carbon copy; most of volume 4 and volumes 5 to 7 are handwritten)
    (microfilm copy available)
  - Correspondence and other papers
    (microfilm copy available of papers from July 1850 to 1872)
    - Undated 1828-1850, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - 1851-1863, 41 folders (Box 2)
    - 1864-1872, 36 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Letters from Mr. and Mrs. Henry Bunce to Maria Bunce Buell, Jane Bunce den Bleyker, and Paulus den Bleyker 1856-1857 (Box 3)
    - Clippings (Box 3)
    - Manuscripts, unidentified and undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Genealogical miscellanea (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence with A.C. Van Raalte (Box 4)
    - Deed of land between Lucius Lyon and Elisha Hall (Box 4)
    - Notes on Dutch settlement (Box 4)
    - Miscellanea re. the Netherlands (Box 4)
    - Maps, plats, etc.
      - Land ownership maps of parts of Holland and Park Townships, Ottawa County, Michigan (Box 4)
      - Plats of parts of Kalamazoo, Michigan, including John den Bleyker Subdivision (Box 4)
      - General maps of Denmark Township, Tuscola County, Michigan, and Comstock and Kalamazoo Townships, Kalamazoo County, Michigan (Box 4)
      - Map of Eijerland, Texel, Netherlands (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Receipts and statements
    - 1843-1872, 35 folders (Box 4)
- John and Anna den Bleyker
  - Correspondence and other papers
    - Undated 1852-1869, 9 folders (Box 4)
    - 1870-1936, 41 folders (Box 5)
  - Receipts and statements
    - Undated 1838-1934, 25 folders (Box 6)
  - Other activities and miscellaneous
    - Holstein Breeders Association papers 1882-1890 (Box 6)
    - Poetry (Box 6)
    - Michigan Female Seminary
      - Papers 1890-1937, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Dodge Fund file 1889-1901 (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
      - Printed material (Box 6)
    - School papers (Box 6)
    - Historical essays, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- den Bleyker family
  - Legal papers
    - 1849-1858, 15 folders (Box 6)
    - 1859-1909, 17 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Other family materials
    - Estate papers (General) (Box 7)
    - Estate papers (John den Bleyker) (Box 7)
    - Estate papers (Kryn Broere) (Box 7)
    - Notebooks (personal and financial) of Paulus den Bleyker, 1 boxes (Box 7)
    - Notebooks, poetry books, and diary of Martha den Bleyker (Box 8)
    - Notebooks (personal and financial) of John den Bleyker (Box 8)
    - Notebooks (personal and financial) of Anna den Bleyker (Box 8)
    - Notebooks of den Bleyker family members (authorship uncertain), 1 boxes (Box 9)
    - Printed material (published in the Netherlands) (Box 9)
    - Printed miscellanea (Box 9)
    - Miscellanea re. den Bleyker Collection, 2 folders (Box 9)
      (include drafts of translations of den Bleyker-Van Raalte correspondence)
    - Photographs (Box 9)
      (portraits, many unidentified; one group portrait includes Lucinda Hinsdale Stone, see also UAx)
    - Indentures, deeds, mortgages, plats, etc., 5 folders (Box 10)
      (include account book of Balch den Bleyker)
Related Material
Since the papers of the den Bleyker family and Nathaniel Aldrich Balch and family were received from the same donor, there were many instances in which portions of one collection were mixed with the other. Anyone interested in either den Bleyker or Balch would no doubt find it worthwhile to look at both collections, since the relationship of these individuals to each other was close.